<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Documenting Texas Music</title>
    <description>This site publishes the oral histories and interviews we conduct for the Texas Music Museum.
</description>
    <link>http://schmidtmjames.github.io//</link>
    <atom:link href="http://schmidtmjames.github.io//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 04 May 2016 22:13:18 -0500</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 04 May 2016 22:13:18 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Alvin Fielder</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Alvin Fielder currently resides in Jackson, MS, but spoke to me while he was in Austin performing at the February 2016 No Idea festival.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Mr. Fielder moved to Houston in the mid-1950s to pursue a pharmacy degree at Texas Southern in the 3rd Ward. Although in his late teens, he quickly integrated himself into Houston jazz and rhythm and blues scenes. He became the drummer for Puma Davis, who led the band at the Eldorado, one of the elegant, postwar middle class black ballrooms in the Bayou city.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Amongst many things, Mr. Fielder discussed the richness of the Houston R&amp;amp;B and bebop scene in Houston during the 1950s. Bebop was being played everywhere, he remembered, and the city was full of talent. Some musicians, like Arnett Cobb, already had a significant career and had returned home. Others went on to record for important labels and became (or were already a) part of the national–and international–story of jazz history: Don Wilkerson, Henry Boozier, Joe Sample, G.T. Hogan, Jimmy Harrison, Joe Curtis, and Richie Goldberg.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fielder noted that there were also significant local players who never came to the awareness of the public outside of Houston. J.D. Norris, a tenor saxophone player who played like early Sonny Rollins; Alexander Sample (Joe’s brother), piano; and Perry Deal, a pianist who reminded Fielder of Muhal Richard Abrams and who he declared “was the most creative piano player to come out of Houston.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;em&gt;Throughout our discussion, Mr. Fielder stressed the importance of environment. University jazz programs aren’t the right environment for the progress of the music, he argued.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;First of all, he contended, jazz’s context was crucial to its origins:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AF:&lt;/strong&gt; This music…it’s like magic. It just sprung up after slavery. There was no roots for it. African musicians aren’t that good, not really. They were brought here to slavery. I guess the American experience really had a great deal to do with it. Only in America could this music be made. As Art Blakey said, only in America could this music could be created. Only, only in America. It was created in Africa. Of course, you’ve gotten certain things, but then you got the European side too. Especially the Italian thing and the Spanish thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;While discussing his own background, he also emphasized the crucial working environment of the generation of postwar bebop musicians that he came of age with:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AF:&lt;/strong&gt; I can remember when I was in high school…I lived in a very nice neighborhood…but going to school I had to pass through some other neighborhoods…I walked to school sometimes…I was usually driven to school, but you had those joints and those dives and the music was playing early in the morning. You would hear it. It’s in the air. And then, of course, the juke boxes had jazz AND rhythm and blues on it. You’d get Charlie Parker being played, Dizzy Gillespie, all bebop stuff. Dizzy Gillespie’s big band mainly, Charlie Parker’s quintets. I didn’t hear any Thelonious Monk, though [laughs]…I didn’t hear any Bud Powell. Some other players: Earl Bostic’s music and stuff. BUT when you think of the Earl Bostic band, think of it, think of who came out of that band. Do you know who came out of that band?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MJS:&lt;/strong&gt; Coltrane came out of that band.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AF:&lt;/strong&gt; That’s just one. Stanley Turrentine, Wynton Kelly, Jimmy Cobb, G.T. Hogan, a bass player from Washington. He had all jazz musicians. Louis Jordan’s band was the same way. When you think of B.B. King’s band, it was all jazz musicians. Jimmy Merrit was in that band, George Coleman, Charle Lloyd. Think of Ray Charles’s band: all jazz musicians. Ray Charles plays great alto. He’s recorded two or three tracks…he really sounded great on alto. His piano playing was good. He sounded a lot like Nat King Cole at first…Jazz was the music. George Adams came through rhythm and blues. Sam Rivers, Hank Mobley, all those guys came through rhythm and blues. It was different. It’s not like the rhythm and blues today. It started changing in the 60s: lesser musicianship. I can remember when I first saw B.B. King’s band. All the bands would come to Meridian at least once a month. B.B. King would come through once a month. Ray Charles, Big Joe Turner, Gatemouth Brown. There was this route. I used to talk to these guys and the first first I talked to was Jimmy Merrit with B.B. King and he was the one who told me about Clifford Brown. Now this is about 1948, 1949. He told me about Philly Joe Jones and he told me about Jimmy Smith’s drummer…those were the musicians he was talking about. There was this East Coast band, the Joe Morris band. Guess who was in it? Philly Joe Jones, Percy Heath, Johnny Griffin. All the great jazz musicians played in rhythm and blues bands except Jackie McLean and Sonny Rollins, probably. Think about it: it was a great starting factor because the rhythm and blues bands were swinging. They don’t swing any more. Rhythm and Blues, of course, turned into rock later on. There’s a difference in the rhythms, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;AF on R&amp;amp;B vs. Jazz vs. R’n’R rhythms:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;audio controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;source src=&quot;/assets/Rhythms.mp3&quot; type=&quot;audio/mpeg&quot; /&gt;
  Your browser does not support the audio tag.
&lt;/audio&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MJS:&lt;/strong&gt; What was your experience in rhythm and blues bands?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AF:&lt;/strong&gt; Well, I was born in Meridian, Mississippi. Are you familiar with Lovie Lee Watson? He was born there. I played in his band. Lovie Lee and his Funky Three. That was the name of his group. Lovie Lee went on to play with Muddy Waters. A lot of great musicians came out of Meridian. Big Jimmy Cole called his band Jimmy Cole and his Mighty Rockers. However, they were playing jazz. Jay Crosby: tenor player from Meridian, went into the army. You remember the Pittsburgh Courier, the Chicago Defender? They had write ups on him. Great tenor player. He wound up in Chicago. He played like Illinois Jacquet. Bunk Lane was a white tenor player from Meridian. Sounded a lot like Stan Getz. Do you remember Dexter Gordon…Dexter’s Deck and all that? That’s how Bunk Lane sounded. Great white tenor player. But his father was band director for the Meridian schools. He moved to Hawaiaa and joined the navy, but he could have gone to New York and really played. You had several drummers from there. You remember Freddie Waits? Freddie was from Jackson. We both started playing around the same time.”&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;em&gt;1950s Houston was another important enviroment for Fielder:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;audio controls=&quot;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;source src=&quot;/assets/Houston.mp3&quot; type=&quot;audio/mpeg&quot; /&gt;
  Your browser does not support the audio tag.
&lt;/audio&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
(note: the sound quality is not perfect, since the interview took place on a backyard porch and one can also hear grackles, the screen door, and neighborhood noise.)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Apr 2016 03:43:59 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://schmidtmjames.github.io//interviews/2016/04/25/Alvin-Fielder.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://schmidtmjames.github.io//interviews/2016/04/25/Alvin-Fielder.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>interviews</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
